Guide to the Special Assistant to the President Records, 1975-1988
Duke University. University Archives
Special Assistant to the President records 1975-1988
Duke University. University Archives
Duke University. Office of the President. Special Assistant to the President.
3.0 linear feet Extent: 3,000 Items
The Special Assistant to the President was responsible for ensuring University compliance with equal employment opportunity and affirmative action legislation. Materials in the collection include administrative records, correspondence, financial and statistical reports, memoranda, newspaper clippings, and other materials primarily documenting Office of Civil Rights (OCR) compliance and complaints associated with Title IX of the Education Amendments of 1972 to the Civil Rights Act of 1964, compliance with the Department of Health, Education and Welfare (HEW), and fair hiring practices for faculty. Dates of the materials range from 1975 to 1988, but a majority of the materials range from 1978-1981.
UA.03.03.0002
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
For a period of twenty-five years from the origin of the material, permission in writing from the office of origin and the University Archivist is required for use. After twenty-five years, records that have been processed may be consulted with the permission of the University Archivist.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Provenance
The Special Assistant to the President Records were received by the University Archives as a transfer in 1990 and 1993.
Historical Note
The Special Assistant to the President was responsible for ensuring University compliance with equal employment opportunity, Title IX of the Education Amendments of 1972 to the Civil Rights Act of 1964, which prohibits sex discrimination against students and employees of educational institutions, and affirmative action legislation.
Collection Overview
Materials in the collection include administrative records, correspondence, financial and statistical reports, memoranda, newspaper clippings, and other materials primarily documenting Office of Civil Rights (OCR) compliance and complaints associated with Title IX, compliance with the Department of Health, Education and Welfare (HEW), and fair hiring practices for faculty. Dates of the materials range from 1975 to 1988, but a majority of the materials range from 1978-1981.
Subject Headings
Duke University; Duke University. Office of the President. Special Assistant to the President; Faculty – United States
Related Material
Office of Institutional Equity records, 1979-[ongoing].
University Archives. Duke University.
Opportunity Development Center records, circa 1970-1984.
University Archives. Duke University.
Inventory of the Women's Department of Health and Physical Education Records, 1923 – 1976.
University Archives. Duke University.
Contents of Collection
- Container List
  - Applications (Blank), undated (Box 1)
  - Availability - Faculty/Staff, 1978 (Box 1)
  - Committee on Women Faculty in the Medical Center, 1987 (Box 1)
  - Employment Analyses - Back-up Material, 1978 Jun (Box 1)
  - Employment Analyses - HEW, 1978 (Box 1)
  - Faculty - Promotions, Tenure Decisions (HEW), 1977-1978 (Box 1)
  - Faculty Recruiting, 1975-1978 (Box 1)
  - Faculty Recruiting, 1978-1979 (Box 1)
  - Faculty Recruiting, 1979-1980 (Box 1)
  - Faculty Recruiting - Dept. of Chemistry, 1978-1979 (Box 1)
  - Faculty Recruiting - Dept. of Philosophy, 1978-1979 (Box 1)
  - Faculty Recruiting - Director of International Studies, 1978-1979 (Box 1)
  - Faculty Recruiting - General, 1978-1979 (Box 1)
  - Faculty Recruiting - Mathematics, 1978-1979 (Box 1)
  - Faculty Recruiting - Political Science, 1978-1979 (Box 1)
  - Faculty Recruiting - Public Policy Sciences, 1978-1979 (Box 2)
  - Faculty Recruiting - Romance Languages, 1978-1979 (Box 2)
  - Faculty Recruiting - Sociology, 1978-1979 (Box 2)
  - Faculty Recruiting - Zoology, 1978-1979 (Box 2)
  - Faculty Recruiting Survey, 1975 (Box 2)
  - HEW Compliance - Supporting Data (Departmental), 1979 Oct (Box 2)
  - HEW Compliance Review, 1978 (1 of 2) (Box 2)
  - HEW Compliance Review, 1978 (2 of 2) (Box 2)
  - HEW Compliance Review, 1979-1980 (Box 2)
  - HEW Compliance Review - Copies of Enclosures, 1979 Oct (1 of 2) (Box 3)
  - HEW Compliance Review - Copies of Enclosures, 1979 Oct (2 of 2) (Box 3)
  - HEW Compliance Review - Supporting Data (Professional & Grad School), 1979 Oct (Box 3)
  - Medical Exit Interviews, 1988 (Box 3)
  - OCR Title IX Compliance Review, 1981 (Box 3)
  - OCR Title IX Compliance Review, 1981 (Box 3)
  - OCR Title IX Compliance Review, 1983 (Box 3)
  - OCR Title IX Compliance Review - Employment Complaint & Student Insurance, 1983 (Box 4)
  - OCR Title IX Compliance Review Continuation, 1982 (Box 4)
  - OCR Title IX Review - Drafts & Supporting Data, 1980-1981 (Box 4)
  - OCR Title IX Review - Exhibit 1, 1980-1981 (Box 4)
  - Operating Budgets - DUAA, 1978-1979 (Box 4)
  - Petition - Council of East Campus Presidents, 1980 (Box 4)
  - President's Report Department Submittals, 1986 (Box 4)
  - Report to President on Medical School, 1986 (Box 4)
  - Terminations, 1977 (Box 5)
  - Title IX: Club and Intramural Census, 1979 (Box 5)
  - Title IX Complaint - Data on Athletics, 1980-1981 (Box 5)
  - Title IX Complaint - Drafts, Notes, Misc. Data, 1980-1981 (Box 5)
  - Title IX Complaint - Internal Investigative Report, 1980-1981 (Box 5)
  - Title IX Complaint - Kooyman-Brew Notes, DOE Correspondence, 1980-1981 (Box 5)
  - Title IX Correspondence & News Clippings, 1975-1979 (1 of 2) (Box 5)
  - Title IX Correspondence & News Clippings, 1975-1979 (2 of 2) (Box 5)
  - Title IX Draft Material, 1976 (Box 5)
  - Title IX Draft Material Report, 1976 (Box 6)
  - Title IX: Policy Interpretation on Athletics, 1979 Dec (Box 6)
  - Title IX Policy Interpretation, 1978-1979 (Box 6)
  - Title IX Review Statements, 1976 (Box 6)
  - Title IX: Rules for Change in Status - Intercollegiate Sports, 1979-1980 (Box 6)